Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Sutton, Kathleen: Audio Recording, 1974 April 22 and May 9 (Cassette 227, 227A & 227B)
    This interview was conducted on April 22 and May 9, 1974 by Scott Weir at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center in Manhattan, New York. Topics include Kathleen Sutton’s childhood in Ireland; her family's immigration to the United States (US); her early life and work experiences in New York, New York; leisure activities and social organizations in which she participated; her marriage and family; her experiences during Prohibition and the Great Depression; and her views on religion and politics. Sutton discusses her childhood in Limerick, Ireland, including the fact that her family was very poor; her father's employment on the docks in Limerick; and her education. She recalls her immigration to the US, including departing from Queenstown, Ireland on the SS Majestic; traveling with her sister and her nephew; and having difficulty obtaining citizenship in the US due to a discrepancy in her name on the ship’s manifest. She recalls her early experiences in New York, including feeling lonely and homesick for the first year; being teased due to her accent; being confused about how to use money; interacting with people of different races for the first time; and finding that a majority of the people she met were nice to her because she was from Ireland.
    Sutton discusses her work experience, including her first job making paper flowers; her employment as a packer at both Macy’s and B. Altman and Company; her promotion to the mail order department of B. Altman and Company and her dislike of the job due to the lack of socializing; and her limited employment as a telephone operator after her marriage and her dislike of working overnight. She discusses leisure activities in which she participated, including seeing movies and Broadway shows before her marriage; having picnics at Fort George in Manhattan; attending soccer games; and taking walks with her husband every night. She recalls her involvement with the Friends of Irish Freedom, including collecting money to support the 1916 Easter Rising in Ireland; attending dances sponsored by the organization; feeling obligated to join because she was Irish; and continuing to support the movement towards a unified Ireland even though the organization no longer existed at the time of the interview.
    Sutton discusses her husband and his life, including his work as an electrician; his political views; and his involvement in the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers Local 3. She discusses their children and grandchildren, including their two daughters and their personalities and the participation of one of their grandsons in the civil rights movement.
    Sutton discusses her experiences during Prohibition and the Great Depression, including distilling moonshine at a bungalow on Staten Island; obtaining alcohol through a friend who owned a speakeasy; rationing meat and sugar; and learning to use Oleo because of the difficulty obtaining real butter. She discusses religion, including the fact that a majority of her neighbors in the US were Catholic; that priests were seen as infallible; and that she was unlike the rest of her community in that she was not religious. She discusses her dislike of the British because of their treatment of the Irish and the fact that much of her family in Ireland supported the Germans during World War II because they provided weapons to the Irish during the Easter Rising. She recalls her husband’s involvement in local politics; her association with many local politicians, including Fiorello La Guardia; and her belief that Irish politicians were trustworthy, while other politicians were only concerned with votes.
    See also: Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York,New York and the United States; Passage; and Politics.
    Department stores |x Employees |z New York (State) |z New York.; Depressions |y 1929 |z New York (State) |z New York.; Prohibition |z New York (State) |z New York
  - Sutton, Kathleen: Summary, 1974 April 22 and May 9 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Tamovitz, Israel, Undated (Cassette 133A & 133B, Box 15, Reel 133 (tapes 1-2), Box 26)
    Israel Tamovitz was born Vilna, Russia. He was one of six children and had two brothers and three sisters. His father worked for a freight station in Vilna while his mother stayed home and cared for the children. Tamowitz immigrated to the United States (US) in 1910 in order to avoid being drafted into the Russian Army. He paid an agent to smuggle him out of Russia and traveled to the US, arriving at Ellis Island, New York. He settled in Pennsylvania with his brother. He worked as a salesman both in Russia and in the US. While in Russia, he was an active member of the General Jewish Labour Bund of Lithuania, Poland, and Russia.
    This interview was conducted by Francis Facciolo on March 24. The year and location are unknown. This interview covers Israel Tamovitz’s life in Vilna, Russia; his involvement in the General Jewish Labour Bund of Lithuania, Poland, and Russia; his immigration to the United States (US) in 1910; and some of his life in Pennsylvania. Tamovitz begins by explaining his involvement in the Bund, noting that he learned about the organization through word of mouth; began attending meetings held in the woods; and keeping his coworkers informed about demonstrations and proclamations against the czar. He discusses the relationships among factions within and outside of the organization; the relationship between the people and the police; Tamovitz’s arrest; and his brother’s involvement in the Bund.
    Tamovitz recalls that his initial impression of the US was that of a beautiful, free country in which every person could go where he wanted and stay informed of government policies. He describes the development of an unspecified miners’ union in the Pennsylvania town where he settled; the impact John Mitchell and the miners’ unions had on working conditions; and the decline of mining, which forced workers into other industrial occupations and trades. Other topics include his brother’s immigration to the US and the fate of members of his family that remained in Vilna during World War I and World War II.
    Allgemeyner Idisher arbayṭerbund in Liṭa, Poylen un Rusland.; Coal miners |x Labor unions |z United States.
  - Tannenbaum, Rose (formerly Belle Tannenbaum): Audio Recording, 1973 April 30 (Box 29)
    Rose Tannenbaum was born in 1896 in the Lithuanian region of the Russian Empire. Her grandfather was a lumber merchant. She immigrated to the United States when she was 16 years old. She lived in Lancaster, Pennsylvania; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and New York, New York. She married and had one son. She worked in a wholesale sweater business and belonged to B’nai B’rith International.
    This interview was conducted by Victor Scheluchin on April 30, 1973 at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Rose Tannenbaum’s family and her working life in the United States (US).
    Tannenbaum recounts her reasons for immigrating to the US, including an impending pogrom in her town and general anti-Semitism in the Russian Empire. She recounts immigrating to the US with two of her brothers; her mother and her remaining siblings immigrating to Austria; and her father and grandfather remaining in Lithuania. She recounts settling in Lancaster, Pennsylvania upon her arrival in the US; moving to Philadelphia; working in a five-and-ten; and meeting and marrying her husband. She discusses moving to New York, New York with her husband; his work as a music salesman; and her enjoyment of her work in a wholesale sweater business. Other topics include the deaths of her family in Austria and Israel during World War II (WWII); her travels to Europe before WWII to visit her family; and her attendance at Brooklyn College to study Hebrew and an unidentified school on 14th Street in Manhattan to study Russian.
  - Tannenbaum, Rose (formerly Belle Tannenbaum): Summary, 1973 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Taranto, Raphael, 1975 March 24 (Box 12, Cassette 173)
    Raphael Taranto was born near Sicily, Italy in 1890. He had six sisters and four brothers. He first immigrated to the United States (US) in 1908 and stayed with his brother and uncle but returned to Italy in 1911 to serve in the Italian Army. He married his wife while in Italy and returned to the US in 1918. He worked as a longshoreman and was a member of the International Longshoremen's Association Local 1814. His wife worked in the garment industry and was a member of an unspecified union (likely the International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union).
    This interview was conducted by John Jentz on March 24, 1975 at the Carroll Gardens Senior Center at 380 Court Street in Brooklyn, New York. A second interviewer, identified as Frank, joins the interview after 20 minutes. Raphael Taranto speaks predominantly in Italian and is assisted by a translator, John Laccari. The volume of this recording fluctuates.
    This interview covers Raphael Taranto’s immigration to the United States (US) in 1908; his return to Italy to serve in the Italian Army between 1911 and 1918; and his work as a longshoreman in the US. Taranto begins by describing the reasons he immigrated to the US, explaining that he believed that he could have a better life there. He discusses working as a longshoreman in Brooklyn, New York until 1955 and joining Local 1814 of the International Longshoremen’s Association (ILA). Other topics include the development of Local 1814 and the ILA; segregation and discrimination among different immigrant groups; and a comparison of living conditions in New York City in the past and at the time of the interview.
  - Terranova, Benny: Audio Recording, Undated (Cassette 152)
    Benny Terranova was born in 1912 in Brooklyn, New York and was one of eleven children. His parents were born in Sicily, Italy. His father owned a bakery in Brooklyn. Terranova graduated from Primary School 103 and attended Stuyvesant High School in Manhattan for a year and a half before leaving school to work with his father. He worked as a baker and as a longshoreman. He was a member of an unspecified Italian bakers’ union and the International Longshoremen’s Association (ILA). He was an official and president of an unspecified local (likely Local 1814) of the ILA. He married in 1940.
    This interview was conducted by Joan Granucci and Martin Lesser. The date and location are unknown. The interview covers Benny Terranova’s childhood, his family, his working life, and his union activity. Terranova discusses his childhood; his education; his father’s insistence that he leave school at age 14 to help in the bakery; and his father’s indulgence of his children. He discusses becoming interested in organizing his father’s bakery as a member of an unspecified Italian bakers’ union; working to organize other local bakeries; and becoming disillusioned with the industry. He recounts his decision to become a longshoreman; his first jobs as a longshoreman; and unsafe conditions on the waterfront. He recounts alternating between working on the waterfront and in the bakery for four years before switching to working as a longshoreman full time after seeing the work of the International Longshoremen’s Association (ILA) to improve working conditions. He discusses the frequent strikes organized by the ILA and how these led to steady increases in wages in the 1940s and early 1950s. He describes the different jobs he held on the waterfront and his rise through the ranks, from working in the holds of the ships to being a superintendent working in an office. He discusses officials of the ILA, in particular Anthony Anastasio and Joseph Ryan. He describes the ethnic and racial demographics of the longshoremen in New York; the organization of ILA locals along racial and ethnic lines; and difficulties in organizing different racial and ethnic groups into one local. He discusses the issues he felt were most important for longshoremen at the time of interview, including health and safety and improvement of pensions.
  - Terranova, Benny: Index, Undated (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Thompson, Lizziemae, Undated (Box 6, Cassette 207 & 207A)
    Lizziemae Thompson was born in Wilson, North Carolina in 1928. She was one of eight children. Her father worked at R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company and her mother managed the household. She graduated high school in 1947 and attended Pfeiffer State Teacher’s College in Misenheimer, North Carolina for one year on a scholarship. She married in 1947 and had two children. She migrated to New York, New York in 1949 and lived on both 121st and 122nd Streets between 7th and 8th Avenues in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan. She worked as a substitute teacher at Primary School 68 and another unnamed school in New York City. In 1959, she began working as a dietitian at Montefiore Hospital in the Bronx. She was an active member of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union and was elected shop steward from 1960 to 1967.
    The interviewer, date, and location of this interview are unknown. Other people can be heard conversing in the background. This interview covers Lizziemae Thompson’s childhood in Wilson, North Carolina; her migration to New York, New York; her work in Montefiore Hospital in the Bronx; and her involvement in Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union. Thompson begins the interview by describing her childhood in Wilson, including her grandmother’s plantation and the education and occupations that her siblings pursued. She explains that she worked as a children’s caretaker for multiple summers, noting that the family she worked for would go to Montauk, New York in order to visit the children’s father, who was in the Navy. She notes that these visits inspired her love for New York and prompted her to move to the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan with her husband and children in 1949. Thompson briefly describes working as a substitute teacher for Primary School 68 in the Bronx, New York and another unnamed school but notes that she went to work at Montefiore Hospital in 1959 in order to acquire better wages and more stable work.
    The rest of the interview focuses on Thompson’s experience at Montefiore Hospital and her involvement in Local 1199. She details her work in the dietary department managing and serving patients’ meals. She emphasizes the different ways in which men and women were treated on the job; discusses tensions between the medical and support staff; and these tensions leading to difficulties in union organization. Thompson describes the environment at Montefiore, noting the hierarchy of hospital employees; the issues and hazards of working with the hospital food trucks; the tight-knit community formed in the dietary department; and the ways her department’s delegates aided other hospital departments. She emphasizes the relationship between the union and the hospital, including reception of the union in various departments within the hospital; the impact the union and strikes had on working conditions and hours in the hospital; strikes in 1958 and 1959, and the community’s support for the union; the active involvement of black and Puerto Rican members in the union; and important members of Local 1199, in particular Teddy Mitchell and Leon Davis.
  - Thompson, William, Undated (Box 25, Cassette Missing)
    William Thompson was born in Florida. He joined the Army during World War I and was stationed in France, where he unloaded ships and guarded prisoners of war. He worked in a drugstore in Boston, Massachusetts after the war and migrated to New York, New York on September 3, 1923, where he worked unloading goods from ships. He worked on a freight train and as a railroad porter with the Pullman Palace Car Company. He was a member of the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters and the American Legion. At the time of the interview, he volunteered with the American Red Cross and other unspecified non-profit organizations.
    The date and location of this interview are unknown. The interviewer is likely Shirley Stow. This interview covers William Thompson’s childhood in Florida; his experience in the Army during World War I; his migration to New York, New York; his work as a porter for the Pullman Palace Car Company; and his volunteer work at the time of the interview. Thompson begins with a summary of his childhood in Florida, including living with his aunt after his mother died; picking beans on his aunt’s farm; playing baseball, swimming, and fishing during his leisure time; and going to church and Sunday school. He recalls acquiring a job on a freight train when he was 17 years old and being drafted into the Army during World War I. He explains that although his particular battalion did not experience racial discrimination, black soldiers in other regiments reported such treatment. He recounts being discharged from the Army in 1919 and settling in Boston, noting few black residents in the area. He describes migrating to New York, New York on September 3, 1923 and finding work unloading goods from ships for two years.
    Thompson describes his work as a porter for the Pullman Palace Car Company, including traveling throughout much of the United States and parts of Canada and Mexico; making beds and cleaning rooms; the seniority basis for rail assignments; his membership in the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters; a train engineers’ strike near Kansas City, Kansas that halted a train in the middle of its journey; the way in which the Pullman Company attempted to replace the porters with Filipino immigrants; and the state of the railroad after the development of transportation alternatives. He concludes by recounting his volunteer activities at the time of the interview for the Salvation Army and the American Red Cross.
    Porters |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Torres, Tony, Undated (Box 18, Cassette 215 & 215A)
    The interviewer, dates, and locations of these two interviews are unknown. These interviews cover Tony Torres’ migration from Puerto Rico to New York, New York, and his work in haberdasheries and a bakery. Torres mentions that he, his mother, and his brother migrated to the New York, New York in 1918 in search of better economic opportunities. He describes being sent to a series of orphanages after his mother died during the influenza epidemic in 1918. He notes that while he did learn English in the orphanages, he also lost his native Spanish while living there and mentions that the orphans tended to stick together regardless of their nationality. Torres explains that he worked various odd jobs until he found stable work in a haberdashery, emphasizing how specific trades were usually associated with specific social networks or ethnic groups. He describes getting a job at a bakery through the newspaper; joining an unspecified bakers’ union (likely the Journeymen Bakers Union of New York); being elected shop steward; and enduring a seven month strike for better wages and work hours. He notes that, at the time of the strike, the union was composed of mostly independent locals that kept to themselves whereas, at the time of interview, the locals presented a more united front within the industry.
    Torres explains that Puerto Ricans who migrated to New York remained mostly in tight-knit groups; migrants emphasized the importance of tradition, especially the retention of the Spanish language; and that their children integrated with other ethnic groups, diluting some of the strong Puerto Rican traditions. He notes the lack of organization and leadership in the Puerto Rican population, which he believes contributed to their lack of a political presence, particularly in New York City. Other topics include the relationships between different immigrant populations where he lived and worked; New York City politics, predominantly focusing on Fiorello La Guardia and Vito Marcantonio; the surge in Puerto Rican migration to the United States in the 1940s; Puerto Rican involvement in politics; the development of labor unions, with emphasis on the inclusion of immigrant and minority groups; the mechanization of bakery work and its impact on bakers; his leisure time activities; and a comparison between the importance of religion to his generation of Puerto Ricans and younger generations.
    See also: Ethnicity; Family; Leisure; Politics; and Unionization.
  - Tossio, Primo: Audio Recording, 1975 April 8 (Box 1, Cassette 164)
    Primo Tossio was born in Rome, Italy and was the oldest of eight children. His father was a longshoreman. Tossio attended four years of school before joining the workforce, selling newspapers and shoveling coal for ships. He immigrated to the United States in 1926 when he was 16 years old. He worked as a longshoreman and was a member and superintendent of an unspecified union (likely the International Longshoremen’s Association).
    This interview was conducted by Howard Harris at the West End Italian Club in Manhattan, New York on April 8, 1975. This interview covers Primo Tossio’s childhood in Rome, Italy; his immigration to the United States (US) in 1926; and his work as a longshoreman in New York, New York. Tossio describes his childhood in Italy, noting that his education was cut short when his father fell ill and he had to work in order to support his family. He recounts immigrating to the US illegally in January 1926; arriving in Baltimore, Maryland; and being assisted by local Italians on his way to New York. He describes his job as a longshoreman; his work in both Brooklyn and Staten Island; and the difficulty of loading ships due to the organizational work that accompanied it. He recounts joining an unspecified union (likely the International Longshoremen’s Association); gaining a greater sense of job security; moving into management positions including hatch foreman and superintendent; and sending most of his salary to his family in Italy. Tossio focuses on the relationship between the workers and the stevedore, noting that the stevedore was paid more money. He explains that the stevedore would not hesitate to fire someone whom he felt was not working hard enough and that he maintained a small group of favored workers whom he consistently employed.
  - Tossio, Primo: Index, 1975 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Unger, Margareta, 1974 April 23 (Box 25, Box 23, Cassette 247, 247A & B)